Guide to the M. Moran Weston Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
M. Moran Weston Papers,
1824-1994
Weston, M. Moran, 1910-
75 linear ft. (ca. 89.000 items in 179 boxes.
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library. New York, NY.
4077412
Biographical Note
Episcopal clergyman and social activist, Columbia University A.B., 1930; Ph.D, 1954. He was born in North Carolina, the son and grandson of Episcopal ministers, and he studied under his mother, Catherine Perry Weston, at St. Luke's Parochial School in Tarboro NC, which had been founded by his maternal grandfather, the Rev. John W. Perry, in 1882. Following in the footsteps of his mother and his father, the Rev. Milton Moran Weston, he attended St. Augustine's Junior College in Raleigh NC from which he graduated in 1928 as valedictorian.
In 1928, Weston enrolled at Columbia University in New York City from which he graduated in 1930. His career as a social activist and clergyman was centered in that city. During the 1930s, he studied at General Theological Seminary in New York, at the Episcopal Divinity School in Philadelphia, and at Union Theological Seminary in New York from which he received a Bachelor of Divinity degree in 1934 and later a M. Div. He continued his studies at the New School for Social Research, 1935-1937, and at Columbia University for a Ph.D in social history in 1954.
During the 1930s and 1940s, Weston participated in several student and community organizations that supported Negro, interracial, youth, civic, and labor causes. In 1934 he served as chairman of the National Conference on Problems of Negro College Students. He also worked as a caseworker and supervisor for the New York City Department of Social Welfare from 1935 to 1941. In 1941 he began writing his column, "Labor Forum", which appeared in THE AMSTERDAM NEWS for almost ten years. In 1942, following the attack on Pearl Harbor, he was asked to manage the efforts of a community labor group, The Labor Victory Committee, to obtain jobs in the war industries for Negroes, especially those led by A, Philip Randolph, founder and head of the Pullman Car Workers Union, which led to the issuance of the historic Executive Order 8802 by President Roosevelt.
He managed the first Negro Freedom Rally held in Madison Square Garden with wide public support and the participation of Duke Ellington, Pearl Primus, and Paul Robson. This was a presentation of a Negro history pagent written by Yale University graduate Owen Dodson which attracted an overflow audience in the Garden with over 5,000 persons on 49th Street, unable to enter. The second Negro Freedom Rally the following year, also in Madison Square Garden, had more than 19,000 people in attendance. He was also asked to organize support for a third public rally in Madison Square Garden against colonialism in Africa, sponsored by Africa House, which drew about 14,000 people. During the same war period, he was asked to manage the African Dance Festival, presented to a sold-out audience at Carnegie Hall with a performance by Asadata Dafora, a noted African drummer, sponsored by the African American Council with Eleanor Roosevelt and Mary McLeod Bethune as guests of honor.
From 1947 to 1957 he was a licensed real estate broker. In 1947 he helped foung the Carver Federal Savings and Loan which became the Carver Federal Savings Bank, a public company traded on the American Stock Exchange. His tenure at Carver ran until 1998, during which time he served as president from 1968 to 1969, chairman of the board from 1980 to 1995, and chairman emeritus in 1998.
In 1953 he obtained a grant from the Fund for the Republic to recruit and hire a non-black Episcopal Clergyman to visit selected churches in the south to encourage suppport for the expected result of Brown vs. the Board of Education in 1954. For this undertaking, he wrote a background paper and guide which was published by the National Council of the Episcopal Church as JUST RIGHT AND NECESSARY.
Weston's professional association with St. Philip's Church began in the mid-1940s. The parish, which had been founded in 1809 and whose history dates to 1697, was then one of the largest parishes in the Episcopal Church. In 1945, he helped found its Federal Credit Union. From January 1948 through September 1951, he served as business manager of the church, leaving to become executive secretary of the Department of Christian Social Relations of the National Council of the Protestant Episcopal Church, a position he held until 1957. In June 1951, Weston was ordained an Episcopal priest and in September 1957 he returned to St. Philip's as the sixth rector in its 147-year history. He served until retiring in 1982 as Rector Emeritus.
As a staff officer of the National Council of the Episcopal Church (1952-1957) he obtained, in 1956, a grant from the Fund for the Republic to produce and transport a traveling exhibition on the role of the Episcopal Church in promoting the cause of social and political justice in the U.S.A. during the 20th century. Starting with its first showing at the Cathedral of St, John the Devine in New York City, the exhibition was presented at some 19 key Episcopal churches.
As part of his many responsibilities, he created the Community Service Council of Greater Harlem, Inc. (CSC) which was the social service arm of his ministry and served as its president from 1959 to 1985. Under his direction the Council, in cooperation with the church, constructed a community center and parish house in 1970 of 30,000 sq. ft. on 4 levels and air-conditioned. In 1970 he also founded the Upper Manhattan Day Care and Child Development Center with specifically designed facilities and staff for 65 pre-school and 110 after-school pupils daily. Two newly constructed residences (St. Philip's Senior House, 200 apartments, and St. Philip's on the Park, 260 apartments) under a corporation and board independent of the church opened in 1974 and 1975. The Greater Harlem Nursing Home, under a separate corporation of which he was the founder and president until 1986, was completed the following year. In 1979 the church rehabilitated ten adjoining apartment buildings which it had owned since 1910 when African-Americans first began to move to Harlem. The building had been bought by the church during its relocation from 25th Street and 7th Avenue to 134th Street west of 7th Avenue under the leadership of the 4th Rector of the church, the Rev. Mr Bishop (1886-1934).
In 1985 Weston opened Bishop House, the first unit of 20 residential apartments for independent living for the mentally challenged, followed by Weston House in 1988 and the Weston House Transitional Living Community in 1989. A third senior citizens' apartment building on Convent Avenue at 131st Street, Weston Terrace, was opened in 1988. Dr Weston also served as president of the Douglass Circle Development Corporation, sponsored by the New York City Housing Partnership, which constructed two subsidized condominium buildings of 600 apartments at 110th Street and Central Park West in 1988.
From the 1950s through the 1990s Weston served on numerous boards including the NAACP Legal Defense Fund, the Leake and Watts Children's Home, the New York City Mission Society, the Community Service Council of Greater New York, Columbia University, the Phelps Stokes Fund, the Mt. Sinai Medical School and Hospital, St. Augustine's College in Raleigh NC, CARE, the Urban League of Westchester County, the Foreign Relations Association, the Cathedral of St. John the Devine, the Harlem Cultural Council, and the Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture.
Weston was also active as an advocate for community redevelopment in Harlem and for affordable housing for all Americans. He founded Urban Ventures, Inc. in 1959 and Harlem-on-the-Hudson Development, Inc. in 1969 to advance the redevelopment of Harlem. He initiated Housing for People, Inc. in 1980 and the National Association for Affordable Housing (NAFAH) in 1985. At the request of NAFAH Congressman Charles Rangel introduces in Congress in 1995, 1996, and 1997 his proposed amendment to the Constitution to make a home a right of all American citizens. The proposed amendment is known as the "Home Amendment". As a civic project he organized the MAS Breakfast Group from 1975 to 1995 which offered networking possibilities for black leaders in New York.
Dr Weston's scholarly accomplishments include a position as a tenured Professor of Social History in the Department of African and African-American Studies at the State University of New York at Albany from 1968 to 1977, and as a Visiting Professor at the University of Ife, Nigeria in 1978. His publications include EPISCOPALIANS AT WORK IN THE WORLD (1952), his dissertation SOCIAL POLICY OF THE EPISCOPALIAN CHURCH IN THE TWENTIETH CENTURY (1964), and WHO IS THIS JESUS? (1973), and numerous articles, pamphlets, and chapters of books. His public speaking engagements included presentations throughout the country at conferences, conventions, churches, civic organizations, universities, colleges, and secondary schools.
Numerous awards and commendations have been given him including an honorary Doctor of Divinity from the Virginia Theological Seminary in 1964, an honorary Doctor of Sacred Theology from Columbia University in 1969, and an honorary Doctor of Humane Letters from Fordham University in 1988, as well as many awards from Harlem, New York, and national organizations. From 1968 to 1977 Weston held two full-time paid positions, one in Albany and the other in New York City, as well as various volunteer responsibilities.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, documents, oral histories, photographs, audio cassettes, and printed material. Family and personal correspondence; materials related to his secondary, college, and university education; materials related to his tenure at the National Council of the Protestant Church; business correspondence of St. Philip's Episcopal Church and the St. Philip's Community Service Council; bulletins of church services; drafts of sermons and speeches, as well as numerous audio-tapes; manuscripts and publications; correspondence related to the construction and on-going maintenance of several senior-citizen and other community housing; correspondence related to various community redevelopment initives and campaigns for affordable housing; materials related to college courses including oral histories for his Black Family Research project; photographs of St. Philip's Church and of activities of the St. Philip's Community Service Council.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 19 series:
Series I: Weston Family
Series II: Biographical Materials
Series III: Personal Correspondence
Series IV: National Council of the Protestant Episcopal Church
Series V: St. Philip's Church
>Series VI: Community Service Council of Greater Harlem
Series VII: Housing
Series VIII: Harlem Development Projects
Series IX: Carver Savings And Loans
Series X: Boards of Directors and Committees
Series XI: Sermons, Speeches and Invocations
Series XII: Manuscripts and Publications
Series XIII: Teaching
Series XIV: Cataloged Correspondence
Series XV: Photographs
Series XVI: Film, Audiotapes and Casettes
Series XVII: Miscellaneous
Series XVIII: Books
Series XIX: Damaged Files
Subjects
Carver Federal Savings.; Columbia University.; Community Service Council of Greater Harlem.; Episcopal Church.--National Council.; General Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.); Knights of Pythias.--Grand Lodge of New York.; Saint Augustine's College (Raleigh, N.C.); Saint Philip's Church (New York, N.Y.:Episcopal); Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.); Abernathy, Ralph, 1926-1990.; Anderson, Marian, 1897-1993.; Astor, Brooke.; Bailey, Pearl.; Davis, Ossie.; Dee, Ruby.; Delany, Annie Elizabeth, 1891-1995.; Delany, Sarah Louise, 1889-1999.; Edelman, Marian Wright.; Franklin, John Hope, 1915-2009.; Higginbotham, A. Leon (Aloyisus Leon), 1928-; Hoving, Thomas, 1931-; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Jordan, Vernon E. (Vernon Eulion), 1935-; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968.; King, Coretta Scott, 1927-2006.; Koch, Ed, 1924-; Lindsay, John V. (John Vliet); McCall, H. Carl.; Morrison, Toni.; Motley, Constance Baker, 1921-; O'Neal, Frederick, 1905-1992.; Osofsky, Gilbert, 1935-1974.; Powell, Adam Clayton, 1908-1972.; Randolph, A. Philip (Asa Philip), 1889-1979.; Robinson, Jackie, 1919-1972.; Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Runcie, Robert A. K. (Robert Alexander Kennedy), 1921-2000.; Rustin, Bayard, 1912-1987.; Schuyler, George S. (George Samuel), 1895-1977.; Sutton, Percy E.; Tutu, Desmond.; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964.; Watts, Andre.; Harlem (New York, N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Harlem (New York, N.Y.)--Social life and customs.; Harlem (New York, N.Y.)--Statistics, Vital.; African American churches.; African American public worship.; African Americans--Housing--New York (State)--New York.; African Americans--New York (State); African Americans--Religion.; Older people--Services for--New York (State)--New York.; Children--Services for.; Church work with African American youth--New York (State)--New York.; Civil rights.; Community development.; Community health services--New York (State)--New York.; Housing.; Public welfare.; School boards--African American membership.; Sermons, American--African American authors.; Social service--Societies, etc.; Social work with African Americans.; Religious institutions--New York (State)--Harlem (New York); Accounts.; Announcements.; Annual reports.; Articles.; Audio cassettes.; Awards.; Badges.; Bills (invoices).; Brochures.; Curriculum vitae.; Deeds.; Diaries.; Diplomas.; Essays.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
Boxes 1-154 & 156-179 are shelved off-site. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
1997 M-1997 Papers Weston, M.M. Gift
- Series I: Weston Family
  - Family records and genealogy (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Copies of deeds of family property, 1824, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with family members (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Weston, Milton M. Bible used at his ordination, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Weston, Milton M. Materials relating to his ministry, 1906-1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Weston, Milton M. Materials relating to his various churches, 1909-1915 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Weston, Milton M. Materials relating to Knights of Pythia's, 1947-1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Weston, Milton M. Newspapers and Magazine Articles (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Howe, Robert S. Letter & Newspaper Clippings (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ladd, William Palmer Passports etc. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Final Proposal (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Forward Movement Pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Articles (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series II: Biographical Materials
  - M. Moran Weston Biographies & Curriculum Vitae, 1940-1979 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - M. Moran Weston Biographies & Curriculum Vitae, 1980- (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - M. Moran Weston Articles on M. Moran Weston, 1971- (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Miriam Drake Weston Pamphlets on Father-Child Relationship (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - M. Moran Weston Family Materials (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - M. Moran Weston Saint Augustine's Senior College, 1926-28 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - M. Moran Weston Materials from Retreat at Virginian Theological Seminary, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - M. Moran Weston Saint Stephen's College, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Weston, M. Moran Correspondence with his father regarding Columbia College, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Columbia College Official Correspondence, 1928-1941 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Columbia College Student Activities, 1929-1930 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Columbia College Yearbook, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Columbia College Class of 1930 Alumni Activities, 1978-1993 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - General Theological Seminary Official correspondence, 1931-1938 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - General Theological Seminary Official correspondence, 1934-1941 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Weston, M. Moran Various student records, 1933-1950 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Union Theological Seminary Alumni Activities (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Weston, M. Moran Various student materials from divinity schools, 1931-1935 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Weston, M. Moran Various student materials from divinity schools, 1931-1935 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Weston, M. Moran Various student materials from divinity schools, 1931-1936 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Weston, M. Moran Various student materials from Union Theological Seminary, 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Columbia University Offical correspondence, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Columbia University Various student materials, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Columbia University Various student materials, 1949- (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Columbia University Graduate School student papers, 1949 and 1950 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Weston, M. Moran Correspondence relating to his ordination, 1947-1950 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Weston, M. Moran Correspondence relating to his ordination as deacon, June 1950 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Weston, M. Moran Correspondence relating to his ordination as priest, December 1950 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Virginia Theological Seminary Doctor in Divinity Honoris Causa, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Columbia University Doctor of Sacred Theology Honoris Causa, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Weston, M. Moran Various honors and awards, 1977-1988 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Fordham University Doctor in Humane Letters Honoris Causa, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Weston, M. Moran Various honors and awards, 1990-1992 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Columbia University Citation (Box 173, Folder 962)
  - Weston, M. Moran Ethopia, 1974, (1 volume (Diary)) (Box 173)
- Series III: Personal Correspondence
  - Weston, M. Moran Personal correspondence, [n.d.] and 1929-1982 (Box 7, Folder 47-56)
  - Weston, M. Moran Personal correspondence, January 1983 - December 1984 (Box 8, Folder 57-63)
  - Weston, M. Moran Personal correspondence, January 1985 - December 1986 (Box 9, Folder 64-68)
  - Weston, M. Moran Personal correspondence, 1987 - June 1989 (Box 10, Folder 69-73)
  - Weston, M. Moran Personal correspondence, July 1989 - December 1991 (Box 11, Folder 74-79)
  - Weston, M. Moran Personal correspondence, July 1992 - 1994 (Box 12, Folder 80-83)
  - Weston, M. Moran Personal correspondence: The Boule Sigma Pi Phi Fraternity, 1976-1992 (Box 12, Folder 84)
  - Weston, M. Moran Personal correspondence: Kappa Alpha Psi Fraternity, 1978 and 1979 (Box 12, Folder 85)
  - Weston, M. Moran Personal correspondence: NAACP-New Rochelle Branch, 1981 and 1982 (Box 12, Folder 86)
  - Weston, M. Moran Personal correspondence:One Hundred Black Men Inc. 1980-1982 (Box 12, Folder 87)
  - Weston, M. Moran Personal correspondence:New Rochelle Heights Association, 1961-1990 (Box 12, Folder 88)
  - Weston, M. Moran Personal correspondence:New Rochelle Heights Racquet and Recreartion Club, 1979-1992 (Box 12, Folder 89)
  - Weston, M. Moran Personal correspondence:Chief Simeon Adebo (Box 12, Folder 90)
  - Weston, M. Moran Personal correspondence:Laura Yergan (Box 12, Folder 90A)
  - Weston, M. Moran Personal correspondence:Arts related projects including Gallaery M, 1927- (Box 12, Folder 91)
  - The White House Invitation (Box 174, Folder 968)
- Series IV: National Council of the Protestant Episcopal Church
  - Scrapbooks of various activities, 1950-1956, (1 volume) (Box 13, Folder 92)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1956 (Box 13, Folder 93)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 13, Folder 94)
  - Reports of the Church on Alcoholism, 1946-1958 (Box 13, Folder 95)
  - Social Relations Workshop Correspondence Papers, etc. 1951 (Box 173, Folder 958)
  - "Episcopalians At Work In The World", (Book) (Box 174, Folder 970)
- Series V: St. Philip's Church
  - Publicity brochures (Box 14, Folder 96)
  - Yearbooks, 1933, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 97)
  - Reverend Shelton Hale Bishop Obituary, 1962 (Box 14, Folder 98)
  - Saint Philip's Families at Worship and Work for 172 Years, ca. 1982 (Box 14, Folder 99)
  - Reaching Out, ca. 1982, (Correspondence) (Box 14, Folder 100)
  - Reaching Out, 26 February 1982, (T.ms. (darft, photocopy)) (Box 14, Folder 101)
  - Reaching Out, April-August 1982, (T.ms. (darft, photocopy)) (Box 14, Folder 102)
  - Reaching Out, May-August 1982, (T.ms. (darft, photocopy)) (Box 15, Folder 103)
  - Reaching Out. Editorial comments by John Hewitt, 1982, (T.ms. (darft, photocopy)) (Box 15, Folder 104)
  - Reaching Out. Editorial comments by Archibald Murray, 1984, (T.ms. (darft, photocopy)) (Box 15, Folder 105 & 106)
  - Reaching Out: An Epic of the People of Saint Philip's Chruch, ca. 1986, (Photocopy ) (Box 15, Folder 107)
  - Vestry minutes and correspondence, 1948-1950 (Box 16, Folder 108)
  - Vestry minutes and correspondence, 1951, 1952, 1958, 1959 (Box 16, Folder 109)
  - Vestry minutes and correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 16, Folder 110)
  - Vestry minutes and correspondence, 1963, 1964 (Box 16, Folder 111)
  - Vestry minutes and correspondence, 1965-1967, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 112)
  - Vestry minutes and correspondence, 1970-1974, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 113)
  - Vestry minutes and correspondence, 1977-1979 (Box 17, Folder 114)
  - Vestry minutes and announcements, 1980-1982 (Box 17, Folder 115)
  - Vestry. Building Committee, 1948-1959 (Box 17, Folder 116)
  - Vestry. Building Committee, 1960 (Box 17, Folder 117)
  - Vestry. Building Committee, 1961 (Box 17, Folder 118)
  - Vestry. Building Committee, 1962-1964 (Box 17, Folder 119)
  - Vestry. Stewardship Committee, 1961 (Box 17, Folder 120)
  - Vestry. Finance Committee minutes and correspondence, 1978- 1981 (Box 17, Folder 121)
  - Vestry. Housing Committee minutes and correspondence, 1981 (Box 17, Folder 122)
  - Sundry Report Sheets and Business Office Receipts, 1977-1979 (Box 18, Folder 123)
  - Financial Statements unaudited and audited, 1959-1969 (Box 18, Folder 124)
  - Financial Statements unaudited and audited, 1970-1976 (Box 18, Folder 125)
  - Financial Statements unaudited and audited, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 126)
  - Financial Statements unaudited and audited, 1978-1979 (Box 18, Folder 127)
  - Financial Statements unaudited and audited, 1980-1982 (Box 18, Folder 128)
  - St. Philip's Federal Credit Union, 1961-1983 (Box 18, Folder 129)
  - Management Report, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 130)
  - Various Blank Forms and Stationery. (Box 19, Folder 131)
  - Parish staff meeting minutes, 1957-1961 (Box 19, Folder 132)
  - Undated communications. (Box 19, Folder 133)
  - Cypress Hill Cemetery correspondence, 1916-1982 (Box 19, Folder 134)
  - Business correspondence, 1945-1949 (Box 19, Folder 135)
  - Business correspondence, 1950-1957 (Box 19, Folder 136)
  - St. Philip's planning council, 1955-1957 (Box 19, Folder 137)
  - Business correspondence, 1958 (Box 19, Folder 138)
  - Business correspondence, 1959 (Box 19, Folder 139)
  - Business correspondence, January - February 1960 (Box 20, Folder 140)
  - Business correspondence, March - April 1960 (Box 20, Folder 141)
  - Business correspondence, May - June 1960 (Box 20, Folder 142)
  - Business correspondence, July - September 1960 (Box 20, Folder 143)
  - Business correspondence, October - December 1960 (Box 20, Folder 144)
  - Business correspondence, January - February 1961 (Box 20, Folder 145)
  - Business correspondence, March - April 1961 (Box 21, Folder 146)
  - Business correspondence, May 1961 (Box 21, Folder 147)
  - Business correspondence, June - August 1961 (Box 21, Folder 148)
  - Business correspondence, September - October 1961 (Box 21, Folder 149)
  - Business correspondence, November - December 1961 (Box 21, Folder 150)